Guide to the Faculty papers and memorabilia, 1823-2001 MS2132.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Faculty papers and memorabilia collection
1823-2001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
McNeil, Hiram Colver
Ruggles, William
MS2132.UA
8.5 Linear Feet
This collection includes notebooks, diaries, lectures, medical research papers, correspondence, photographs, plays, booklets, awards, and and memorabilia.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired through office transfers and donor gifts.
Historical or Biographical Note
This artificial collection was created to manage small amounts of faculty papers and memorabilia that are too small to be separate collections of their own.
Collection Scope and Content
The collection contains personal papers, course material, etc. from former faculty members of The George Washington University. The material is separated into series by faculty member.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series, Memorabilia and Faculty Papers
Washington (D.C.); Lectures; Diaries; Education; Civil defense; American Red Cross; World War, 1939-1945; Medical ailments; Medicine; Arena Stage (Organization: Washington, D.C.); Photographs; Welling, James Clarke; George Washington University. School of Education; Allison, Burgiss; Columbian University; George Washington University--History; Ruediger, William Carl; Washington, George; George Washington University; Marvin, Cloyd Heck
- Memorabilia, ca.1826-2001; MS2132 Series 1; 2.5 Linear feet (Box 15, Box 2, Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains hats, spectacles, and army figurines. They range in date from approximately 1826 to 2001. The materials concern memorabilia that faculty have donated.
  - Colonial hat from the anniversary of Washington's birth, 02/22/1999-02/22/2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Two black, felt tri-corner Colonial hats with gold trim from GW 200th anniversary of Washington's birth, February 22, 1999. The hats have "Happy Birthday George!" and the GW logo printed on the sides. The third hat is identical of the other two, except for the date on the side is February 22, 2001.
    Formerly ACC#747. (One hat from 2001 was added in February 2001.)
  - Glasses (spectacles) of Rev. Burgiss Allison, 1826 ca. --01/28/1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Burgiss Allison, a Trustee of Columbian College from 1821-26, was born in Bordentown, New Jersey on August 17, 1753. A clergyman by profession, he became a convert to the Baptist faith early in life and began to preach when he was sixteen years old. He studied at Rhode Island College (now Brown University) but did not graduate, but was awarded an honorary degree from Brown in 1804. He had charge of a small congregation in Bordentown where he established a classical boarding school which attained a great reputation. In 1796 he withdrew from his teaching and devoted several years to inventing. Improvements to the steam engine and its application to navigation resulted from his efforts. In 1801 he resumed his school and his pastorate, but ill health forced him to relinquish both. Rev. Allison was elected chaplain of the U.S. House of Representatives in 1816 and later became chaplain at the Navy Yard in Washington, D.C. He was also one of the secretaries of the American Philosophical Society for several years, helped found the American Academy of Fine Arts, and was vice president of the Baptist convention. Rev. Allison's daughter married Col. James Lewis Edwards, and Virginia Edwards Parker (the late wife of John E. Parker) is a direct descendent of this couple. Rev. Allison died in Washington on February 20, 1827. Materials include Rev. Allison's pair of spectacles with case. In the Gilbert Stuart portrait, he is holding them in his left hand. Spectacles in good condition, red case in poor condition. Also, included is the "Program for the Acceptance of the Gilbert Stuart Portrait of Burgiss Allison". Formerly ACC#961.
  - George Washington's army figurines, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    The three sets of Washington army figurines were donated for display in the Memorabilia Room by Stephen Joel Trachtenberg, President of The Washington University. They include 23 figures of Washington's Guard marching, 23 figures of Washington's guard firing, 10 figures of Washington's artillery, and some shrubbery. They are approximately one inch in height and painted. Label on boxes states "Berliner Zinnfiguren Werner Scholtz Washington's Artillerie Auswischen 170/26/3 (10 Figuren)" and "Berliner Zinnfiguren Werner Scholtz Washington's Garde, im Feuer 170/26/2 (23 Figurern)".
    Formerly ACC#739.
  - Eyeglasses and case belonging to Robert Vincent, 1945 ca. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Materials include eyeglasses and case belonging to Robert Vincent, GW professor of chemistry. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Gas Mask, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    This item is a gas mask that was potentially used on GW campus during the Anti-war riots. A letter that came with the object notes: " This gas mask was presented to Professor Gillette by Matt Weiss and other students in the American Studies program in commemoration of the summer of 1970 tear-gassing of GW students by the DC police during anti-Viet Nam war protests. This item was donated to the University Archives by Barnard Mergen.
  - Stained glass from St. Mary's church, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
- Personal papers, 1823-1990; MS2132 Series 2; 6 Linear feet (Box 8, Box 15, Box 11, Box 9, Box 13, Box 10, Box 12, Box 3, Box 5, Box 7, Box 14, Box 6, Box 4)
  This collection contains notebooks, diaries, lectures, medical research papers, correspondence, photographs, plays, booklets and awards belonging to various GW faculty members. The material ranges in date from 1823 to 1998.
  - Syllabus of lectures by Prof. Welling on English literature at Columbian College, 04/19/1873-05/24/1873 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Apparently notes taken by W.B. Nichols in the course. The back of the notebook has various notes from an earlier time, on the subjects of grammar, medicine, philosophy, and accounts. Nichols was an 1874 graduate in law from Columbian College; James Clarke Welling was President of Columbian College, and professor of history and international law, 1871-1894. Gift of De Forest Ormes, 1964. Bound in quarter brown leather with marbled paper over boards. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 69.
  - Course of lectures on celestial mechanics delivered at Columbian College, 1893 -1894 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Course of lectures on celestial mechanics delivered at Columbian College by George William Hill (1838-1914); copied from the original manuscript by Edgar Frisby (1837-1927). Astronomer and mathematician; Frisby was professor of mathematics, U.S. Navy, 1878-1899, and taught at Columbian University, now George Washington University. Formerly Ind. Ms. Bd. 85 f.
  - Medical research papers, 1955 -1990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    This series contains four volumes of medical research papers by Dr. Ariel Hollinshead (M.A., 1955; Ph.D. 1957 from George Washington University), focused primarily on various cancers. Formerly ACC#176 and RG#7.2.1.
  - GW correspondence with Vincent, 1940 -1953 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Materials include correspondence, certificates, photos (including President Marvin 10th anniversary dinner), World War II material and artifacts belonging to Robert Vincent (professor of chemistry). They range in date from 1937-1979. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Power of Attorney - Robert Vincent to Ralph M. Vincent, 08/1942 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - World War II era material, 1946 -1953 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Materials include a card to Robert Vincent (professor of chemistry) from students, signed ""The students of Chemistry 21A&B, 22x and their instructors"; letter from Army thanking Vincent for his military service (1946); pamphlet on the contribution of the Chemist to victory in WWII (1946); Organized Reserve Corps questionnaire and bulletin (1946); discharge from U.S. Army Reserves (1953). Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Certificate - Phi Kappa Phi membership of Robert Vincent at Cornell University, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Materials include a certificate for Phi Kappa Phi membership by Robert Vincent at Cornell University, 1940. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Certificate - American Society for Industrial Security, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Materials include a certificate from the American Society for Industrial Security, 1957. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Award presented to Vincent by GW President Lloyd Elliott, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Materials include an award presented to Vincent by GW President Lloyd Elliott, 1979. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Photos and negatives of Vincent and family (?), undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Materials include photos and negatives of Vincent and family (?), including a news clipping. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Photo of dinner in honor of Cloyd Heck Marvin, 05/10/1937 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Materials include a panorama photo of a dinner in honor of the 10th anniversary of Cloyd Heck Marvin as GW President at the Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C., May 10, 1937. Formerly ACC#1032.
  - Note and syllabus for first aid courses for GW faculty taught by Ira Hansen Thelma Hunt, et al, 1940 ca. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Materials include first aid and civil defense booklets belonging to Ira B. Hansen (professor of zoology, 1936-1954). They range in date from 1937-57. Formerly ACC#883.
  - American Red Cross First Aid booklet, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - American Red Cross First Aid booklet, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - American Red Cross "Instructors Outline: First Aid Courses", 1941 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - United States Office of Civilian Defense "Protection Against Gas", 1941 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    Materials include first aid and civil defense booklets belonging to Ira B. Hansen (professor of zoology, 1936-1954). This item also includes American Red Cross handout on gas and chart of chemical warfare agents. They range in date from 1937-57. Formerly ACC#883.
  - United States Office of Civilian Defense "First Aid" handbook, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - United States Office of Civilian Defense "Air Raid Wardens" handbook, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - United States Office of Civilian Defense patch, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Samuel Tyler manuscript, 1870 ca. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Manuscript (452 pages) titled "Blossom of Science: Being an Example of Science Considered from a Theistic View" by Samuel Tyler (professor of law), c.1870. Tyler was born in 1809 in Maryland, and taught law at the university from 1867-78. He was the author of several works on metaphysics and died in 1878. (Biographical information taken from "Historical Catalogue of the Officers and Graduates of the Columbian University.") Formerly ACC#251.
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1823 -1855 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include outgoing correspondence and range in date from 1823-55. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Incoming correspondence, A-C, 1826 -1841 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include incoming correspondence and range in date from 1826-41. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Incoming correspondence, D-H, 1825 -1832 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include incoming correspondence and range in date from 1825-32. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Incoming correspondence, I-R, 1822 -1834 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include incoming correspondence and range in date from 1822-34. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Incoming correspondence, S-Z, 1826 -1838 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include incoming correspondence and range in date from 1826-38. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Memoranda of tour [from Washington, D.C. to Newport, Rhode Island, 07/16/1827-08/22/1827 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include notebooks recording a trip from Washington to Newport, Rhode Island July 16-August 22, 1827. Formerly ACC#258.
  - Papers, 1823 -1852 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    William Ruggles was Professor of Mathematics at Columbian College (now GW University) from 1823 to 1833. Dr. Ruggles was born in Rochester, Massachusetts in 1797 and died in Washington D. C. in 1877. A graduate of Brown University he became a tutor at Columbian College in 1822 and became the chair of mathematics and natural philosophy in 1827. He remained in this position until his death. He served Columbian College for a fifty year period. William Ruggles was also noted for his generous contributions to charities, missionary bequests. He received the honorary LL.D. from Brown in 1852. Materials in this collection include his William Ruggles journals and letters to and from Ruggles. The materials include receipts, notes on books and lectures, drafts of corresponence, and range in date from 1823-52. Formerly ACC#258.
  - William Ruggles Correspondence, 1830-1831; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    General
    Two letters written by James Ruggles to his Brother William while William was a professor mathematics and natural philosopy at Columbian College. The first letter relays the circumstances of their father's death; the second discusses a rough winter and day-to-day events in the life of James, who was a tavern owner in Rochester, Massachusetts.
  - Arena Stage plays and clippings, 1945 -1952 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Edward Mangum was a professor of Drama at George Washington University and a founder of Arena Stage. See also an article in the Alumni Review magazine from Winter 1961 (old ACC#894). Materials include a list of plays produced at Arena Stage (August 1950- May 1952), original stationary of Arena Stage, newspaper articles about the Arena Stage (1950-52), and correspondence (1945-1949). See also an article in "Washington History" (call number F191.C72; v.10:1). Formerly ACC#707.
  - Correspondence and booklet on Mount Vernon Players, 1936 -1946 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Edward Mangum was a professor of Drama at George Washington University and a founder of Arena Stage. See also an article in the Alumni Review magazine from Winter 1961 (old ACC#894). Materials include correspondence (1946) and Mount Vernon Players 10th Anniversary booklet, 1936-1946. See also an article in "Washington History" (call number F191.C72; v.10:1). Formerly ACC#707.
  - Correspondence and articles, 1944 -1998 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    Edward Mangum was a professor of Drama at George Washington University and a founder of Arena Stage. See also an article in the Alumni Review magazine from Winter 1961 (old ACC#894). Materials include correspondence (1944-1948, 1998), an article in Players Magazine, "Shakespeare in Shirt Sleeves" by Edward Mangum (March 1948), an article in Talent Review, "So you Don't Like Church Dramatics?" by Edward Mangum (September 13, 1947), and musical direction for The Taming of the Shrew (April 1947). See also an article in "Washington History" (call number F191.C72; v.10:1). Formerly ACC#707.
  - Medical recipies collected by Burgiss Allison, 1826 ca. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Burgiss Allison, a Trustee of Columbian College from 1821-26, was born in Bordentown, New Jersey on August 17, 1753. A clergyman by profession, he became a convert to the Baptist faith early in life and began to preach when he was sixteen years old. He studied at Rhode Island College (now Brown University) but did not graduate, but was awarded an honorary degree from Brown in 1804. He had charge of a small congregation in Bordentown where he established a classical boarding school which attained a great reputation. In 1796 he withdrew from his teaching and devoted several years to inventing. Improvements to the steam engine and its application to navigation resulted from his efforts. In 1801 he resumed his school and his pastorate, but ill health forced him to relinquish both. Rev. Allison was elected chaplain of the U.S. House of Representatives in 1816 and later became chaplain at the Navy Yard in Washington, D.C. He was also one of the secretaries of the American Philosophical Society for several years, helped found the American Academy of Fine Arts, and was vice president of the Baptist convention. Rev. Allison's daughter married Col. James Lewis Edwards, and Virginia Edwards Parker (the late wife of John E. Parker) is a direct descendent of this couple. Rev. Allison died in Washington on February 20, 1827. Materials include a manuscript notebook in Reverend Burgiss Allison's hand: "Medical recipies collected by Burgiss Allison at different periods since Anno Domini 1793--." It includes a table of contents and forty-six recipes for treating ailments from asthma to whooping cough. Page 11 has a cough syrup recipe by Dr. J(ames) M. Staughton, son of Columbian College's first president William Staughton, and first professor of medicine at the college. Formerly ACC#961.
  - Diaries, 1898 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Hiram Colver McNeil (1866-1937) was a Professor of Chemistry at The George Washington University. He was born October 2, 1866, and received B.S. (1896) and M. S. (1901) degrees from Denison University, where he taught from 1899-1904. He received a Ph.D. from The George Washington University in 1905.
    He served as a research chemist for Columbius Pharmaeal Company, Columbus, Ohio (1905-1907), assistant chemist of the United States Bureau of Chemistry (1907-14), and chemist for the Bureau of Standards (1914-18). McNeil joined the faculty of The George Washington University in 1910 and became head of the Chemistry Department in 1918, continuing in that capacity until 1926, and as Professor of Chemistry until 1933. He was a fellow for the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and a member of the American Chemical Society and the History of Science society.
    Two of Dr. McNeil's sons were graduates of GW: Robert H. McNeil, A.B., 1924 and Harold O. McNeil, A.B., 1932. Dr. McNeil died June 8, 1937 in Los Angeles, California.
    Materials in this collection include diaries (and photocopies of them) that McNeil kept. In the early diarys, Hiram coded his entried. The following is the key to that code:
    A B C D E F G H I J K L M N O P Q R S T U V W X Y Z O P J T I V K N E C G R W H A B X L Z D Y F M Q U S
    They range in date from 1898-1937, and were donated to the University Archives by Robert McNeil, grandson of Dr. McNeil, in 1996.
    N.B. This history note was written in 2005
  - Diaries, 1899 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Diaries, 1900 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Diaries, 1901 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Diaries, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Diaries, 1903 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Diaries, 1904 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Diaries, 1905 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Diaries, 1906 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Diaries, 1907 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Diaries, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Diaries, 1909 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Diaries, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Diaries, 1911 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Diaries, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Diaries, 1913 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Diaries, 1914 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Diaries, 1915 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Diaries, 1916 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Diaries, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Diaries, 1918 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Diaries, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Diaries, 1920 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Diaries, 1921 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Diaries, 1922 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Diaries, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Diaries, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Diaries, 1925 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Diaries, 1926 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Diaries, 1927 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Diaries, 1928 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Diaries, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - Diaries, 1930 (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - Diaries, 1931 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Diaries, 1932 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Diaries, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Diaries, 1934 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Diaries, 1935 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - Diaries, 1936 -1937 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Diaries, 1898 (Box 12, Folder 1)